A Finding Aid to the Paul Bransom Papers, 1862-1985, bulk 1904-1979, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
- Photographs, circa 1885-1976; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 1.3 Linear feet Boxes 7-8, 10
  - Early Photographs of Grace Bond (Bransom), 1905, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 27)
    (Includes photograph taken in Bransom's 23rd St. Studio)
  - Bransom Family Photographs, 1885, 1920-1921, undated; Archival Resource Key; (See also Box 10) (Box 7, Folder 28-29)
  - Bond Family Photographs, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Bransom Pets and Animals Used in Illustrations, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Bransom in Groups with Other Artists, 1904-1952, undated; Archival Resource Key; (See also Box 10) (Box 7, Folder 32)
    (Among those identified are T.S. Sullivant, James Swinnerton, H.A. Magill, Marjorie Organ, T.S. Allen, Gus Mager, Lynn Bogue Hunt, Arthur Fuller, and Bob Kuhn)
  - Portraits of Artist Friends of Bransom, 1920-1971, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 33)
    (Pictured are Gus Mager, Walt Kuhn, Bill Scott, Bud Shannon, Charles Leon, Lynn Bogue Hunt, Raechell Scott, Joe Back, Clarence Tillenius)
  - Paul Bransom on Hunting Expeditions, 1926-1927; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 34)
    (Bransom pictured with E.H. Taylor and J. Frank Dobie)
  - Paul and Grace Bransom's Trip West, 1928; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 35)
    (Pictured are the Bransoms and Toby and Marion Vreeland)
  - Snapshots of Paul Bransom, Grace Bransom, and Others, circa 1910s-1963; Archival Resource Key; (3 folders, including duplicates and negatives; see also Box 10) (Box 7, Folder 36-38)
  - Snapshots of Paul Bransom and Others, 1964-1976, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - Homes and Studios of Paul Bransom, Archival Resource Key (Box 7)
    See also Scrapbooks
    - Brookland, DC (Birthplace), undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 40)
    - 23rd Street Studio, NYC, circa 1900s; Archival Resource Key; (See Box 10) (Box 7, Folder 41)
    - Saratoga Springs, NY, circa 1914-1917; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 42)
    - Canada Lake, NY, 1918-1925, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 43)
      (Includes photo of Bransom painting in studio)
    - Canada Lake, NY, 1926-1936, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 44)
      (Bransom and others pictured)
    - Canada Lake, NY, 1926-1936, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 45)
    - Canada Lake, NY, 1926-1936, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 46)
    - Canada Lake, NY, 1926-1936, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 47)
    - Canada Lake, NY (Duplicates), 1926-1936, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 48)
    - Canada Lake, NY, Black and White Series, 1930, undated; Archival Resource Key; (5 folders; see also Box 10) (Box 7, Folder 49-53)
      (Includes photographs of garden sculpture by Leo Lentelli and a series of photographs by Herbert Lawson)
    - Canada Lake, NY, Color Series, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 54)
      (Bransoms pictured)
    - New York City Apartment, 1962, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Jackson Hole, Wyoming, 1948-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 2)
      (Bransoms and others pictured)
  - Homes of Friends of Bransom, 1943, 1971, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Events, Archival Resource Key (Box 8)
    - Artists Day at Christmas Sales for the Blind, 1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Teton Artists Associated Classes, 1959-1961, undated; Archival Resource Key; (2 folders, including copies) (Box 8, Folder 5-6)
    - Society of Animal Artists Reception, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Weber State College Honorary Doctorate, 1974; Archival Resource Key; (See also Box 10) (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Unidentified People, 1959, 1976, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Unidentified Landscapes, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Animal Photographs, 1968-1972, undated; Archival Resource Key; (See also Box 10) (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Slide Album, 1953-1967, undated; Archival Resource Key; (5 folders) (Box 8, Folder 12-16)
    (People pictured in folders 2, 3 and 4)
  - Photograph Albums from 90th Birthday, 1975; Archival Resource Key; (2 folders; not scanned) (Box 8, Folder 17-18)
  - Works of Art, Archival Resource Key (Box 8)
    - By Bransom, Installation Views, 1962-1975, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - By Bransom, 1948-1972, undated; Archival Resource Key; (4 folders, including negatives; not scanned) (Box 8, Folder 20-23)
    - By Others, 1937-1976, undated; Archival Resource Key; (See also Box 10; not scanned) (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Oversized Photographs (See Box 7, f23, 30, 33, 39, 42, 53; and Box 8, f8, 11, 24), Archival Resource Key (Box 10)
- Scrapbooks, circa 1880s-1970s; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Boxes 8 and 11
  This series consists of two scrapbooks containing clippings, photographs, and exhibition announcements. Neither volume appears to have been made by Bransom himself, and both were part of the donation of Mario Cesar Romero, who had access to the Bransom estate while curating a retrospective exhibition of Bransom's artwork and creating the artwork inventory in Series 4.
  Volume I consists entirely of printed material, mostly clippings and one advertisement for a book illustrated by Bransom, The Argosy of Fables (1921). Clippings also include multiple obituaries. Many of the items in Volume I are duplicated in the Printed Material series.
  Volume II contains exhibition announcements (1929-1931), clippings (1920s-1970s), and photographs (circa 1886-1970). Original photographs have been removed from the scrapbook as a preservation measure and to provide access to Bransom's notes on the backs of photographs. Pages containing the removed photographs have been replaced by photocopies reflecting their original arrangement in the scrapbook. Many of the photographs found in this scrapbook are not found elsewhere in Bransom's papers. Identifications on the scrapbook pages were made by Mario Cesar Romero.
  - Volume I, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 25)
    (Clippings, 1906-1982)
  - Volume II, undated; Archival Resource Key; (See Box 11) (Box 8, Folder 26)
    (Original scrapbook pages containing clippings, exhibition announcements, photographs, and newspaper cartoons dated circa 1886-1979)
  - Items Found Tucked Between Pages of Volume II, undated; Archival Resource Key; (See also Box 11) (Box 8, Folder 27)
    (photographs of Paul and Grace Bransom, photographs of works of art by Paul Bransom, photograph of oil on canvas portrait of Bransom by Dan Green)
  - Photographs Removed from Volume II, circa 1886-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 28)
    (Childhood photographs of Paul Bransom; family members; nanny; Paul and Grace Bransom in Canada Lake, NY home and studio; Paul Bransom painting)
  - Oversized Scrapbook (See Box 8, f26), Archival Resource Key (Box 11)
  - Oversized Items Found Tucked Between Pages of Volume II (See Box 8, f27), Archival Resource Key (Box 11)
- Artwork, 1903-1976; Series 8; Archival Resource Key; 1.7 Linear feet Boxes 8-9, OV 13-22
  This series includes sketchbooks, sketches, drawings, designs, illustrations, cartoons, and prints by Paul Bransom, and artwork of various media by other artists. Most of the artwork depicts wildlife and other animals, although drawings of landscapes, flora, and people are also found.
  Sketches, drawings, and designs encompass the bulk of this series. Three sketching expeditions from the 1920s are represented. The drawings from the Green Tree racehorse stables in Saratoga Springs are accompanied by an essay recounting the trip. Additional material related to the New Mexico Lion Hunt is found in Notes and Writings. The remainder of miscellaneous sketches, drawings, and designs in this series depict a wide range of subjects in various media, from preliminary rough sketches to very finished drawings. Subjects include domestic animals, North American and African wildlife, flora, landscapes, and narrative subjects for illustrations, usually also with animal subjects. Included are works in charcoal, pencil, pastel, watercolor, and ink.
  Prints by Bransom include a series of 26 monotype prints, lithographs, and several woodblock prints, some of which are for bookplates and Christmas cards.
  Many of the works of art in this series are signed and/or annotated by Paul Bransom. A few have an inventory number written on them beginning with "E/B," which refers to the artwork inventory created by Mario Cesar Romero. Additional documentation of this inventory project is found in Personal Business Records. Bibliographic information about Bransom's illustrations is also found in Personal Business records. Notes listing artwork and exhibitions can be found in Notes and Writings. Additional artwork, including illustrated letters and cards, is found in Correspondence. See series descriptions for further details.
  - Sketchbook, circa 1930-1940; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Sketchbook, Cattle Sketches, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Sketches, Drawings, and Designs, Archival Resource Key (Box 8)
    - Alabama Quail Hunt, 1925; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - New Mexico Lion Hunt, 1927; Archival Resource Key; (See also OV 13) (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - Green Tree Stables, Saratoga Springs, NY, 1929, undated; Archival Resource Key; (See also OV 13) (Box 8, Folder 33)
    - Miscellaneous Sketches, Drawings, and Designs, undated; Archival Resource Key; (14 of 19 folders) (Box 8, Folder 34-47)
    - Miscellaneous Sketches, Drawings, and Designs, undated; Archival Resource Key; (5 of 19 folders; see also OV 13-21) (Box 9, Folder 1-5)
  - "News From Bugville" Original Drawing, circa 1905; Archival Resource Key; (See OV 22) (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Design for Starr Family Shield, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Prints, Archival Resource Key (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous Prints, undated; Archival Resource Key; (2 folders; see also OV 22) (Box 9, Folder 8-9)
    - Linoleum Blocks, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Proofs, 1947, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Test Prints, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Artwork By Others, Archival Resource Key (Box 9)
    - Cartoon by Clare Victor "Dwig" Dwiggins, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Painting by O.F. von Feuher, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Painting by Al Gilbert, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Sketch of Bransom by Everett Hibbard, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Bookplate by Lionel Lindsay, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Print by Benson Moore, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Drawing Signed "MCO", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Paintings and Drawings by Charles Sarka, 1903-1910, 1946, 1956, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Print by R. Harmer Smith, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Painting by Marion Terry, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Oversized Sketches, Drawings, and Designs (See Box 8, f32-33; and Box 9, f5), Archival Resource Key (Oversize 13)
  - Oversized Sketches, Drawings, and Designs (See Box 9, f5), Archival Resource Key (Oversize 14)
  - Oversized Sketches, Drawings, and Designs (See Box 9, f5), Archival Resource Key (Oversize 15)
  - Oversized Sketches, Drawings, and Designs (See Box 9, f5), Archival Resource Key (Oversize 16)
  - Oversized Sketches, Drawings, and Designs (See Box 9, f5), Archival Resource Key (Oversize 17)
  - Oversized Sketches, Drawings, and Designs (See Box 9, f5), Archival Resource Key (Oversize 18)
  - Oversized Sketches, Drawings, and Designs (See Box 9, f5), Archival Resource Key (Oversize 19)
  - Oversized Sketches, Drawings, and Designs (See Box 9, f5), Archival Resource Key (Oversize 20)
  - Oversized Sketches, Drawings, and Designs (Copies), Archival Resource Key (Oversize 21)
  - Oversized "News From Bugville" Original Drawing (See B9, f6), Archival Resource Key (Oversize 22)
  - Oversized Miscellaneous Prints (See B9, f9), Archival Resource Key (Oversize 22)
  - Oversized Artwork by Al Gilbert (See B9, f15), Archival Resource Key (Oversize 22)